{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "This man’s associate, Elbert A. Woodward, committed both larceny and forgery while en route to a Connecticut Senate seat. Future presidential candidate Samuel Tilden refused to let this political figure free from prison even after he testified to the Alderman Committee. This man and his New York cronies were depicted as vultures in a Harper’s Weekly political cartoon by Thomas Nast. For ten points, name this “Boss” of the political machine, Tammany Hall.",
      "answer": "William “Boss” Tweed"
    },
    {
      "question": "The oldest-known civilization to have been located in this region was the coastal, fishing-based Chinchorro Culture. This region is home to the world's largest open pit copper mine, Chuquicamata [[choo-kee-kah-MAH-tah]]. In 2003, this region was used by NASA to test its Viking landers due to its similarity to the surface of Mars. This region is believed to have been arid for at least three million years, making it the world's oldest desert. For ten points, name this extremely arid Chilean desert, which prior to 2015 had not seen precipitation for over 500 years.",
      "answer": "Atacama Desert"
    },
    {
      "question": "One of the most lopsided results of this process was led by the slogan “Yes, we love this land,\" which is also the title of the anthem of Norway, which underwent this process in 1905. Another one of these was defeated by the “No Thanks” campaign, which countered the efforts of Alex Salmond and Nicola Sturgeon. An illegal one of these in Spain was preceded by multiple human chains and was followed by the arrest of the president of Catalonia. For ten points, name this democratic process, which sometimes results in new countries.",
      "answer": [
        "Independence referendums or independence referenda",
        "plebiscite"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This composer was the grandson of a philosopher who inspired the Haskalah. This composer's Festgesang [[FEST-ge-SAHNG]] was adapted into the Christmas Carol \"Hark! The Herald Angels Sing.\" During a trip to the United Kingdom, this composer's visit to Fingal's Cave inspired his Hebrides [[HEH-brih-dees]] Overture. This composer collected eight volumes of six Lieder [[LEE-deh]] in his Songs Without Words. For ten points, name this Jewish-German composer who wrote the incidental music for A Midsummer Night’s Dream.",
      "answer": "Felix Mendelssohn 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 7"
    },
    {
      "question": "In support of freedom fighters in this war, U.S. folk group the Almanac Singers, led by activist Pete Seeger, wrote an album of songs such as \"Jarama Valley\" from a U.S. battalion which fought in this war. The use of manufacturing plants in Nazi Germany allowed American companies like GM and Ford to provide twelve thousand vehicles to Falangist [[fah-LAHN-jist]] forces during this intranational war. The Neutrality Act of 1935 prevented the U.S. from intervening in, for ten points, what war between the Republicans and Fascists led by Francisco Franco?",
      "answer": [
        "Spanish Civil War or Guerra Civil Española",
        "Civil War in Spain"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "These people failed to overwhelm European forces who were using the laager, or wagon fort, strategy during the Battle of Blood River. Conquests by these people led to the Mfecane [[MM-feh-KAH-nee]], or “the Crushing,” a period of mass migration of Nguni [[nn- GOO-nee]] people. These people often pincered their opponents using the \"Horn of the Buffalo” formation, implemented by their impi regiments. For ten points, name this Southern African people, once led by King Shaka.",
      "answer": [
        "Zulu people or amaZulu",
        "Zulu Kingdom",
        "Zulu Empire"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This author's alleged incestuous relationship with his half-sister may have resulted in the birth of Elizabeth Medora Leigh. This author's only legitimate child was the early computer scientist Ada Lovelace. This author was described as \"mad, bad, and dangerous to know\" by his mistress Lady Caroline Lamb. This author died of sepsis before he could help attack the Ottoman fortress of Lepanto during the Greek War for Independence. For ten points, name this Romantic poet, the author of \"She Walks in Beauty.\"",
      "answer": "Lord Byron or George Gordon"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man’s raid on Fort Brooke coincided with his ally Micanopy’s [[mih-CAN-oh- pees]] ambush of Francis Dade’s U.S. army regiment. General Thomas Jesup captured this leader under a false “white flag” truce, and the poor conditions at Fort Moultrie led to this man's death. This chief orchestrated the breaking of the Treaty of Payne’s Landing, beginning a second conflict between his tribe and the U.S. army. For ten points, name this Florida chief, the primary Native American leader during the Second Seminole War.",
      "answer": "Osceola"
    },
    {
      "question": "As HUD Secretary, this man urged Fannie Mae and Freddie Mac to buy loans from poor home owners, possibly causing the subprime mortgage crisis. This man noted that George Pataki \"held the leader's coat\" and that \"Cream rises to the top,\" referring to Rudy Giuliani. This man sued Rhode Island over its Quarantine policy, despite having his own lockdown policy. This man faces allegations of sexual harassment and admitted to covering up COVID-19 deaths at nursing homes. For ten points, name this governor of New York.",
      "answer": "Andrew Cuomo 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 7"
    },
    {
      "question": "This organization attempted to exile the author of My Country and the World before he could earn his 1975 Nobel Peace Prize. The head of this organization, Vladimir Kryuchkov, helped lead a 1991 coup to stop the presidential reforms of a man who was championed by a former head of this organization, Yuri Andropov. The NKVD served as the predecessor of this organization, and Russian president Vladimir Putin served as an agent for this organization in the late 1980s. For ten points, name this Soviet equivalent to the CIA.",
      "answer": [
        "KGB",
        "Committee for State Security",
        "or Komitet Gosudarstvennoy Bezopasnosti 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 7"
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Jácome Ratton [[JAH-kohm rah-TOHN]] wrote scathing attacks on this country. An anti-seismic building system from this country features gaiola [[gai-OH-lah]] cages developed after a 1755 event. This country curbed Jesuit power in the Távora Affair, razing noble lands at the \"alley of the salted ground.\" One of history's first restraining orders was issued in this country against the Marquis of Pombal. Signing the Methuen [[meh-THOO- en]] Treaty with England, for ten points, what is this country, the site of the Great Lisbon earthquake?",
        "answer": [
          "Portugal",
          "Portuguese Republic",
          "República Portuguesa",
          "Portuguese Empire"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This French philosopher used the Great Lisbon Earthquake as a counter to the idea that \"this is the best of all possible worlds\" in his Candide.",
        "answer": "Voltaire"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In 1993, an expert in this activity named Nigel Short created the PCA after cutting ties with an international organization. One man refused to participate in a 1975 World Championship in this activity because he espoused a first-to-ten wins schedule rather than a first-to-five wins schedule. In 1972, this event’s championship was held in Iceland and billed as a contest between the U.S. and the U.S.S.R., because it pitted Boris Spassky against Bobby Fischer. For ten points, name this game, whose leading grandmasters include Fabiano Caruana and Magnus Carlsen.",
        "answer": "Chess"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This Russian World Chess Champion was the number one player in the world for the first time at age 20 in 1984 and was number one for nearly twice as many months as any other person in history.",
        "answer": "Garry Kasparov"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The killing of three settlers by this tribe in the town of Cascade led to U.S. army skirmishes during the Sheepeater War. William Clark nicknamed a child from this tribe \"Pompey\" and took care of him after his mother’s death. A member of this tribe, whose leaders included Pocatello, was married to French-Canadian trader Toussaint Charbonneau [[SHAR-ben-no]] and successfully traveled through the Bozeman Pass while serving as a guide with the Corps of Discovery. For ten points, name this Idaho tribe, whose members have included Sacagawea.",
        "answer": "Shoshone or Shoshoni"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Sacagawea began appearing on the U.S. dollar coin beginning in 2000, replacing this women's rights activist.",
        "answer": "Susan B. Anthony 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 7"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During this event, eleven detainees at a colonial detention camp were clubbed to death by guards in the Hola Massacre. In 1952, Governor Evelyn [[EEV-lin]] Baring declared a state of emergency and ordered the imprisonment of Jomo Kenyatta and other rebel leaders in an attempt to prevent this event from occurring. Dedan Kimathi was executed in 1957 after leading an army during this event. For ten points, name this event, an armed struggle between the Kenya Land and Freedom Army and the British authorities.",
        "answer": [
          "Mau Mau Uprising",
          "\"Rebellion\"",
          "\"Revolt\" in place of \"Uprising\"",
          "Kenya Emergency before \"Kenyatta\""
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In 1952, this future dictator of Uganda deployed to Kenya with the King's African Rifles and was later considered to be \"intensely loyal\" to Britain.",
        "answer": "Idi Amin Dada"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "John Husband set this song to \"Hephzibah\" [[HEP-zeh-bah]], while William Walker set this song to the \"New Britain\" tune using shape notes. The wretchedness discussed in this song may represent writer John Newton's realization of his wickedness as a slave trader. This song was published in Olney Hymns and was often used by Baptist ministers in the South during the Second Great Awakening. For ten points, name this Christian hymn whose opening line says that the title entity \"saved a wretch like me.\"",
        "answer": "\"Amazing Grace\""
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "\"Amazing Grace\" has been frequently performed by this social justice folk artist known for her original song \"Diamonds & Rust\" and for leading the crowd in “We Shall Overcome” at the March on Washington.",
        "answer": "Joan Baez"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Gaston Means claimed this man's \"strange death\" resulted from poisoning, not a cerebral hemorrhage or cardiac arrest. In 1923, Charles R. Forbes, who served as director of the Veterans' Bureau in this man's administration, was indicted for fraud, just one of many scandals involving this man. This man had extramarital affairs with Nan Britton and Carrie Fulton Phillips. For ten points, name this U.S. president whose involvement in the Teapot Dome scandal came to light only after he died in office.",
        "answer": "Warren Gamaliel Harding"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "U.S. Secretary of the Interior Albert Bacon Fall was convicted for accepting bribes from oil companies in the Teapot Dome scandal, whose namesake petroleum reserves are located in this state.",
        "answer": "Wyoming 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 7"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This figure took inspiration from the writings of anarchist and fellow countryman Ricardo Flores Magón to adopt the slogan \"Tierra y Libertad.\" Under the guise of a meeting, Jesús Guajardo [[gwah-HAR-doh]] assassinated this resident of Morelos state in 1919 on the orders of Venustiano Carranza. This man, who met with Pancho Villa at the Aguascalientes Convention of 1914, led the Liberation Army of the South against the government of Francisco Madero. For ten points, name this agrarian revolutionary during the Mexican Revolution.",
        "answer": "Emiliano Zapata"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Zapata names an agrarian movement in modern Mexico which originally formed to oppose this 1994 treaty, which created Free Trade Zones with Mexico's northern neighbors.",
        "answer": [
          "NAFTA",
          "North American Free Trade Agreement"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This country was the location of the Cassette Scandal in which Leonid Kuchma [[KOOCH-mah]] was implicated in the kidnapping of a journalist. The Pora! Youth demonstrated in this country in the Orange Revolution, which led to the presidency of Viktor Yushchenko [[yoosh-CHEN-koh]]. Starting in 2014, this country faced separatists in the Donbass and Donetsk People's Republic, and its lands in the Crimean Peninsula were annexed by Vladimir Putin. For ten points, name this neighbor of Russia.",
        "answer": "Ukraine"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "As part of a special agreement at this 1945 conference held in Crimea, Ukraine and Byelorussia became two of the founding members of the United Nations.",
        "answer": "Yalta Conference"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "The Sons of Liberty",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Massachusetts city where they led protests against a 1770 massacre",
          "answer": "Boston"
        },
        {
          "question": "Commodity that they threw into the harbor during a 1773 event in that city",
          "answer": "Tea"
        },
        {
          "question": "Cousin of a future U.S. president who founded the organization",
          "answer": "Samuel Adams"
        },
        {
          "question": "1765 tax on printed materials whose repeal led the original Sons of Liberty to disband",
          "answer": "Stamp Act"
        },
        {
          "question": "British official responsible for implementing that act who was hanged in effigy from the Liberty Tree",
          "answer": "Andrew Oliver"
        },
        {
          "question": "Ship boarded by John Brown which ran aground while pursuing the Hannah",
          "answer": "HMS Gaspee"
        },
        {
          "question": "Tailor and spy who used his slave Cato to send secret information during the Revolution",
          "answer": "Hercules Mulligan"
        },
        {
          "question": "Customs official who was tarred and feathered after a dispute with George Hewes",
          "answer": "John Malcom 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 7 Margaret Thatcher"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Regarding Margaret Thatcher, name the...",
      "prompt": "Name the regarding margaret thatcher, name the......",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Sovereign country she led from London",
          "answer": [
            "United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland",
            "Britain",
            "Great Britain"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Irish independence organization that attempted to kill her at Brighton",
          "answer": [
            "Provisional Irish Republican Army",
            "IRA"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Archipelago she invaded after it was seized by Argentina",
          "answer": [
            "Falkland Islands",
            "Falklands",
            "Islas Malvinas"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Shakespeare-inspired term for a period of strikes that led to her becoming PM",
          "answer": "Winter of Discontent"
        },
        {
          "question": "President of the United Mine Workers who led an 1984-85 strike against her government",
          "answer": "Arthur Scargill"
        },
        {
          "question": "Former PM she defeated in 1975 to become leader of the Conservative party",
          "answer": "Edward Heath"
        },
        {
          "question": "Controversial tax imposed on Scotland that was replaced by the Council Tax",
          "answer": [
            "Community Charge",
            "poll tax"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Secretary of State for the Environment who seized control of the Conservative party from Thatcher in 1990",
          "answer": "Michael Heseltine 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 7"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "The Golden Age of Piracy",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Pirate who owned Queen Anne's Revenge, known for putting lit fuses in his facial hair",
          "answer": [
            "Blackbeard",
            "Edward Teach",
            "Edward Thatch"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Pirate who hid stolen goods at Gardiners Island leading to the legend of his buried treasure",
          "answer": "Captain William Kidd"
        },
        {
          "question": "Privateer and governor of Jamaica who lends his name to a popular brand of rum.",
          "answer": [
            "Henry Morgan",
            "Captain Morgan"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Nine-letter word for certain privateers, taken from the Arawak word for a wooden frame on which they roasted manatees",
          "answer": "Buccaneers"
        },
        {
          "question": "Jamaican city that served as a hub for piracy until it was destroyed by a 1692 earthquake",
          "answer": "Port Royal"
        },
        {
          "question": "Partner of Calico Jack Rackham and Mary Read who stayed her execution due to being pregnant",
          "answer": "Anne Bonny"
        },
        {
          "question": "Adjective given to a series of \"abductions\" in 1627 in which pirates from Algiers took people from Iceland and sold them into slavery",
          "answer": "Turkish"
        },
        {
          "question": "Most successful pirate, a Welshman who captured more than 470 vessels",
          "answer": [
            "Black Bart",
            "Bartholomew Roberts 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 7"
          ]
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The first capture of a foreign ship by a U.S. Navy vessel occurred during this conflict, when the USS Delaware trapped the privateering vessel La Croyable [[kroi- YAH-bluh]] in Great Egg Harbor. The massive bribes requested to meet (20 pts)",
        "Talleyrand during the XYZ Affair led to this conflict. The Convention of 1800, hosted by Consul (10 pts)",
        "Napoleon Bonaparte, ended this two-year conflict and affirmed U.S. neutrality. For ten points, name this undeclared naval war between the United States and France during John Adams’s Presidency."
      ],
      "answer": "Quasi-War"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A fantasia for piano titled Agonia e morte di [this man] was written by Franz Xaver Süssmayr [[SOOS-my-er]] who was also recruited to finish another work by this man in 1791. Georg Fredrich Daumer claimed that this composer was murdered by freemasons for revealing their secrets in an opera in which the (20 pts)",
        "Queen of the Night enlists Tamino to save her daughter. This composer's life was depicted in a namesake film directed by (10 pts)",
        "Miloš [[MEE-loash]] Forman. For ten points, name this Austrian composer of The Magic Flute."
      ],
      "answer": "Wolfgang Amadeus Mozart"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) 116 out of 156 of these things were destroyed in Operation Deadlight while most of the rest were claimed as prizes or sold. The earliest of these things was Wilhelm Bauer's Brandtaucher, and during the Battle of the (20 pts)",
        "Atlantic, Karl Dönitz [[DEHR-nitz]] developed the “wolf pack” strategy with these things. This type of vessel (10 pts)",
        "torpedoed the RMS Lusitania, turning American opinion against the Central Powers during World War One. The Germans conducted “unrestricted submarine warfare” with, for ten points, which naval vessels?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "U-Boats",
        "Unterseebooten"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man was banned from sports at Columbia University after he used the assumed name Henry Lewis to play professionally. Mayor Fiorello La Guardia appointed this man parole commissioner of New York in the last year of his life. This man was the first living person to appear on a (20 pts)",
        "Wheaties box and the first MLB player to have his number retired. This man claimed to be \"the luckiest (10 pts)",
        "man on the face of the earth\" in his retirement speech to a packed stadium in New York. For ten points, name this Yankees first baseman who died from a namesake neuromuscular disease."
      ],
      "answer": "Lou Gehrig 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 7"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "Orders by this man led to the murder of translator Hitoshi Igarashi. Nader Naderpour often recited poetry with this man whose disciple, Morteza Motahhari, founded the Combatant Clergy Association. This man's opposition to the White Revolution led the (*) Shah to send troops to Qom [[GOHM]], and this man's house arrest led to the 15 Khordad Uprising. This man regularly called the U.S. the \"Great Satan\" and published a fatwa calling for (*) Salman Rushdie's murder. Having gained national popularity through the Iran Hostage Crisis, for ten points, who was this Ayatollah?"
      ],
      "answer": "Ayatollah Ruhollah Khomeini"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) With help from Lawrence J. Spagnola, this man wrote an autobiography subtitled My Journey from Rebellion to Redemption. The Christopher Commission was formed after an attack on this man who, in a televised address, repeated the phrase (20 pts)",
        "\"We've got to quit\" after asking the question, \"Can we all get along?\" George Holliday recorded Stacey Koon and three other individuals (10 pts)",
        "beating this man in the aftermath of a high-speed chase. For ten points, name this man whose beating by the LA Police Department led to a series of 1992 riots in Los Angeles."
      ],
      "answer": "Rodney King"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This son of a former Ambassador to Hungary facilitated the rearmament of Israel with Iron Dome Surface-to-Air Missiles during the 2014 Gaza conflict. On his first day in office, this Cabinet member froze all arms sales to (20 pts)",
        "Saudi Arabia and the United Arab Emirates. During his confirmation hearing, this politician promised to continue recognition of (10 pts)",
        "Jerusalem as the capital of Israel rather than returning the U.S. embassy to Tel Aviv. For ten points, name this Secretary of State in the Biden administration."
      ],
      "answer": "Antony Blinken"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "This left-wing figure used the pseudonym \"Gunnar Gaasland\" while living in Norway until the rise of the Quisling government. This head of the SPD resigned after his aide, Günter Guillaume [[gee-YOHM]], was outed as a secret agent for the (*) Stasi [[SHTAH-see]]. This chancellor collapsed weeping at the Warsaw Ghetto monument while on a state visit to Poland. This man won the 1971 Nobel (*) Peace Prize for his work to strengthen European cooperation. For ten points, name this West German chancellor who pursued Ostpolitik while attempting to reconcile with East Germany."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Willy Brandt",
        "Herbert Ernst Karl Frahm 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 7"
      ]
    }
  ]
}